"Side Effects of Osteoporosis Medications
Like Fosamax, Boniva, and Reclast"
Potential lack of efficacy
is not the only reason
why most people prescribed
bisphosphonate drugs
for osteoporosis like Fosamax,
Actonel, Boniva, or Reclast,
may stop taking them
within a year.
There are two rare
but devastating side effects:
osteonecrosis of the jaw
and atypical femur fractures,
that contributed to around
a 50 percent drop
in the use
of this class of drugs
when they came to light.
The New York Times article
noting the decline
explained the reasoning:
"Reports of the drugs
causing jawbones to rot
and thighbones
to snap in two
have shaken many
osteoporosis patients so much,
that they say
they would rather
take their chances
with the disease."
The jaw-rot syndrome
that prevents many
from initiating treatment for
fear of "their jaw falling off"
can severely impact many aspects
of quality of life,
but is exceedingly rare,
affecting at most
one in a thousand patients
treated for osteoporosis.
Atypical femur fractures can
occur more frequently, though,
as many as one in 300 users
treated for three years.
They are called "atypical,"
because they occur
not after a fall or trauma,
but just during
routine activities,
like walking,
twisting at the waist,
or even just standing still.
Your femur,
your thigh bone,
the biggest bone in your body,
just breaks in half.
Too cruel an irony from a drug
that's supposed to protect
your bones.
This is what it looks like
on x-ray.
Ouch.
Bisphosphonates work
by inhibiting the action
of a type of bone cell
called osteoclasts.
Your entire skeleton
is constantly being remodeled
with bone added in some spots
and taken away in others
to conform
to changing demands.
The cells that are continually
laying down new bone
are called osteoblasts,
and the ones
that chisel away old bone
are called the osteoclasts.
It makes sense, then,
that curbing the 'clasts
could prevent bone loss.
But by reducing
the active remodeling process,
bisphosphonates can "freeze"
the skeleton,
allowing for the accumulation
of microcracks over time,
resulting in stress fractures.
Other osteoporosis drugs like
denosumab, sold, as "Prolia,"
prevent the same formation of
osteoclasts in the first place
and have been plagued
by the same kinds
of rare but disturbing
side effects.
As with anything in life,
it all comes down to risks
versus benefits.
How many hip fractures
are prevented
for every femur that snaps?
It depends on your race
and how long
you're on these drugs.
After five years,
in white women,
36 hip fractures
are prevented
for every
atypical femur fracture.
Hispanic women only get half
the benefit, about 18 to 1.
And for Asian women,
it's only about
5 hip fractures prevented
for every femur fracture caused.
The study claims it failed
to accrue enough data
on Black women.
At ten years of drug exposure,
the ratios get worse,
16:1 for white women,
5:1 for Hispanic women,
and only 1.5:1 for Asian women,
meaning that
the devastating fractures
prevented and caused
in Asian women
are nearly comparable.
A nationwide survey
of resident physicians
found that knowledge regarding
osteoporosis diagnosis
and treatment was poor,
with a particularly striking
lack of knowledge
regarding the two
serious drug side effects.
The good news is that
after stopping the drugs,
the risk of femur fracture
rapidly drops by 70 percent
within a year,
leading to the suggestion
that a drug "holiday"
be considered
after a few years
on the drug to help mediate
the risk.